TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
～♪
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
To tell you about Jiguro, I should start
by telling you about my childhood.
（バルサ）
ジグロのことを語るには―
まず 私の幼いころのことから
話さなきゃならないね
カンバルは ヨゴとは違って
豊かな実りをもたらす田畑はない
Unlike Yogo, Kanbal has no fields
that produce bountiful harvests.
All it has are steep mountains
and rocky grasslands.
あるのは 険しい山と
岩だらけの牧草地帯
人々は痩せた土地を耕し
僅かばかりの穀類や芋を作り―
The people make a living
by tilling the poor soil...
...eking out what little grain
and potatoes they can from it...
カンバルヤギを放牧して
暮らしていた
...and by grazing Kanbal goats.
That's the kind of place
I was born and raised in.
私は そんなところに
生まれ育ったんだ
Episode 21
Jiguro Musa
私の父 カルナ･ヨンサは
王室づきの医者でね
My father, Karna Yonsa, was the
royal family's personal physician.
母は ５つのときに
死んでしまったんだけど―
My mother died when I was five,
but thanks to my father...
それでも 父のおかげで―
...I led a happy life,
never wanting for anything.
特に 不自由を感じることなく
幸せな暮らしを送っていた
でも 幼い私は
知る由もなかったんだけど―
I was too young to realize it,
but by that point...
このとき 父はすでに―
...my father was already caught up
in a situation he couldn't get out of.
のっぴきならない事態に
巻き込まれていたんだ
My father, chief physician
to the king of Kanbal...
カンバル王の主治医だった父は―
王位を狙う 王の弟ログサムに―
...had been ordered to
poison the king by Logsam...
...the king's younger brother,
who had his eyes on the throne.
王を毒殺するよう 命じられていた
Logsam had threatened to
kill his daughter if he refused.
断れば 娘を殺すと脅かされてね
And so my father had
no choice but to agree.
それで 父はしかたなく承諾した
However, he knew that as soon as
he'd succeeded in poisoning the king...
けれど 毒殺に成功したところで
その秘密を知る自分と―
娘の命はないことも 理解していた
...his and his daughter's lives would
be forfeit because of what he knew.
ログサムの策略にはまり
孤立無援だった父だが―
Caught up in Logsam's machinations,
my father found himself isolated.
But he had one friend in the palace
that he trusted implicitly.
宮中(きゅうちゅう)において ただ１人
心を許せる友がいた
That man was Jiguro.
それが ジグロだった
ジグロは“王の槍(やり)”と呼ばれ―
Jiguro was a member
of the King's Spears...
王に仕える ９人の武人の１人だ
...a group of nine men
who served the king.
王の槍というのは―
The King's Spears was
comprised of elite spear-wielders...
カンバルにある ９つの氏族領の
筆頭によって組織される―
精鋭の短槍(たんそう)使いのことでね
...the leaders of Kanbal's
nine ethnic tribes.
Jiguro was the youngest man ever
to be elected to the King's Spears...
ジグロは その中でも
最年少で王の槍に選ばれた―
...and was lauded as
Kanbal's most powerful hero.
カンバル最強と
うたわれる英雄だった
Although my father regretted
involving his friend in this terrible plot...
父は 恐ろしい策略に―
友人を巻き込んでしまうことを
悔やみながらも―
ジグロに 意を決して
ログサムの計画を打ち明けた
...he resolved to reveal
Logsam's plot to Jiguro.
（カルナ）私は近いうちに 王に
最後の毒を盛ることになっている
In a matter of days, I will administer
the final dose of poison to the king.
それで 王が死んだあと―
Once the king is dead,
I will inevitably be punished.
自分は 罰を受けなくてはならない
しかし 娘には何の罪もない
But my daughter is
completely innocent.
You are the only one I can turn to.
こんなことを頼めるのは
お前しかいないんだ
I realize that I'm asking you
to do the impossible.
無理な頼みとは分かっている
Ever since my wife passed away, though,
Balsa has been my entire world.
だが 女房が死んでからは―
バルサが 俺の全てなんだ
I beg you, take my daughter
and flee the country.
頼む 娘を連れて逃げてくれ
Apparently, Jiguro refused
my father's request.
（バルサ）
ジグロは 父の頼みを断ったそうだ
当然だ
It's no wonder.
ジグロにとって―
Even though the request came
from Jiguro's close friend...
いくら親友の頼みとはいえ
そいつを引き受けることは―
...to accept would mean forfeiting
not only his status and honor...
地位や名誉を
失うばかりでなく―
身の破滅を 意味するんだからね
...but it would also
spell his own doom.
（バルサ）その日の夕方
宮の兵士が うちにやってきた
In the evening of that same day,
palace soldiers came to our home.
恐らく 父の考えは すでに
ログサムに気付かれていたんだろう
Logsam must have already figured
out what my father was planning.
お前の父親に 頼まれた
I'm here at the request of your father.
Come with me right now.
今すぐ 俺と一緒に来い
（バルサ）一度は 父の頼みを
断ったはずのジグロは―
Although he had initially
refused my father...
...for some reason, he said these words,
took my hesitant hand in his...
なぜか そう言うと
戸惑う私の手を引き―
故郷カンバルをあとにした
...and we left our
homeland of Kanbal.
Jiguro...forgive me...
ジグロ… すまない…
If Jiguro hadn't come
for me when he did...
（バルサ）もし あのとき
ジグロが来てくれなかったら―
...I'm certain that I would
have been killed that day.
私は 確実に殺されていただろうね
それから 私たちは―
We then spent an entire day traversing
the long caves along the Kanbal border...
カンバル国境の 長い洞窟を
１日かけて抜け―
ここ 新ヨゴ皇国の領土に
足を踏み入れた
...eventually crossing into the
territory of the Shin-Yogo empire.
I was completely exhausted,
but I couldn't sleep at all that night.
ひどく 疲れていたはずなのに―
その日は 一睡もできなかったよ
詳しいことは 何一つ
知らされていなかったし―
For one thing, Jiguro hadn't
explained anything to me...
ジグロの ピリピリとした感じが
伝わってきてね
...and his tension was contagious.
ジグロは追っ手がやってくることを
警戒していたんだ
Jiguro was on his guard,
alert for approaching pursuers.
逃亡を初めて ５日後―
Five days after we began our flight,
our first pursuer found us.
最初の追っ手がやってきた
現れたのは 王の槍の１人だった
The man who appeared
was one of the King's Spears.
私は初め その男が
追っ手だとも思わずにいた
At first, I had no idea that the
man was there to hunt us down.
After all, the two of them
were speaking so calmly.
２人が あまりに
落ち着いて話していたからだ
Was it Logsam who
sent you after us?
お前を 討っ手として
よこしたのはログサムか？
Logsam is an even worse
tyrant than I imagined.
ログサムは 想像以上の横逆者だな
That's true.
（王の槍）確かに
But this has given me the chance to
fulfill a dream that I've had for years.
だが そのおかげで―
積年の思いを 果たせる機会を得た
I've always felt a
sense of dissatisfaction...
俺は ずっと
もの足りなさを感じてきた
...over the fact that I haven't
had a chance to challenge you...
お前が 王の槍の
最高位を得てから―
...ever since you achieved the
top rank in the King's Spears.
一度として 優劣を争う機会が
なかったことにな
I also have to question
if it's truly necessary...
そして 命のやり取りに―
...for a spear dance to be
part of a life-or-death struggle.
本当に槍舞が
必要なのかということも！
そうか…
You do, do you?
Perhaps it's because I had
those very same feelings...
俺にも
同じ思いがあったからこそ―
...that I find myself
standing here right now.
俺は今ここにいるのかもしれんな…
フゥ…
ん… 何のつもりだ
What are you doing?
Are you mocking me?
俺を バカにしているのか！
いや 命を懸けた真剣勝負だ
No. This is a genuine
fight to the death.
やああっ！
すまん
I'm sorry.
二度と カンバルには戻れん俺だ
I can never return to Kanbal.
And so I can't bring you
back to our homeland.
故郷の土に帰してやることは
できない…
Let's go.
（ジグロ）行くぞ
It was obvious that Jiguro had
not tried to avoid fighting that man.
（バルサ）あのときの ジグロは―
明らかに 戦うことを
避けようとはしていなかった
その理由は
今もって 分からないけど―
To this day,
I still don't understand why.
But since he had reached
the top at such a young age...
若くして 頂点を極めたがゆえに―
...maybe he wanted, just once,
to see what he was really capable of.
一度は 自分の本当の力を試してみたいと
思ったのかもしれないね
That might have just been
wishful thinking on my part...
それも あの一瞬の戦いが―
自分とは関係ないと信じたい―
私の思い込みだったのかも
しれないけど…
...wanting to believe that the
brief fight had nothing to do with me.
At the same time,
though, it struck me...
ただ 同時に
私は自分の置かれた立場が―
...that my situation was even
more dire than I ever imagined.
想像以上に過酷なものだってことを
感じ取っていたんだ
どうやら自分は―
I realized that my only hope of
survival was to go with this man.
この男に ついていくしか
生きる道はないんだってね
その後 私たちは ヨゴの街に入った
After that encounter,
we entered a city in Yogo...
...to get a replacement spearhead
for Jiguro's broken spear.
ジグロの 折れた槍の穂先を
新調するためにね
あの刀鍛冶は
昔から頑固な男だった
That swordsmith was
stubborn even back then.
At first, he refused to take the job.
初めは 頑として
首を縦に振らなくてね
（ジグロ）できれば これから先
１人も斬らずに済ませたいが―
If at all possible, I'd like
to avoid killing anyone else...
恐らく 何人斬ればいいのか
想像もつかない
...but I have no idea what
that number may even be.
As I know you have the skills to do so,
I would like you to forge me a spear...
（ジグロ）あなたの腕を見込んで
ヨゴ刀に勝るとも劣らぬ槍を一振り―
どうしても 作ってほしいのだ
...that is equal to any Yogo sword.
（バルサ）私は ジグロの
言葉の意味を知るのが怖くて―
The implications of what
Jiguro was saying terrified me...
それ以上 ２人の話を
聞かないようにしていた
...so I avoided listening to
the rest of their conversation.
しばらくして 鍛冶屋は
こうジグロに言った
After thinking a while, the swordsmith
said the following to Jiguro.
"In seven days,
pay me another visit."
“７日後に
またおいでください”とね
The next seven days
seemed like an eternity.
それからの７日間は
とてつもなく 長く感じられたよ
なにせジグロは ひと言も
話をしようとしなかったんだから
For one thing, Jiguro didn't
even try to speak to me.
It's finally started
to snow out there.
（タンダ）
とうとう 降ってきましたよ
（トロガイ）フーッ… そうかい
Has it, now?
どうりで 冷えると思った
I thought it felt colder.
（タンダ）お茶でも入れましょう
２人は上ですか？
I'll go make some tea.
Are those two upstairs?
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
ジグロ！
どうせ もう びしょびしょだよ
Jiguro, we're already soaked to
the bone. Let's rest here a while!
ここで 少し休もうよ
Don't stop! What will
we do if we catch cold?
ダメだ！
風邪をひいたら どうする
Just keep running until
we reach the city.
いいから街まで走るんだ
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
ここに いろ
Stay here.
Well, well.
（ジグロ）そうか…
I knew you would
be the second...
２番手は やはり…
Tagul!
タグル
お前が ここに来るのは
分かっていた
I knew that you would come here.
ログサムに何と言われた？
So, what did Logsam tell you?
Did he order you to kill the
co-conspirators of the physician...
王を毒殺した
医者の仲間を殺してこい―
とでも言われたか
...who poisoned the king?
So, you've taken the
oath not to hear or speak?
“耳なし口なしの誓い”か…
お前が戦いを
好まぬ男だということは―
I know better than anyone that
you're a man who dislikes combat.
誰よりも この俺がよく知っている
妻子を人質に取られたんだな…？
Your wife and children are being
held hostage, aren't they?
（タグル）ぬうっ！
（タグル）ふんっ！
（ジグロ）はあっ！
ううっ！ やあっ！
（ジグロ）でやあああっ！
（タグル）ぐおっ…
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ…
タグル…
Tagul!
お前にも―
So you too...have found
something to protect...at last?
守るべきものが… できたか…
Tagul...
タグル…
（バルサ）
私は ジグロが泣き崩れる姿に―
When I saw Jiguro
break down into sobs...
...I didn't know what I should do.
どうしていいか
分からなくなってしまった
今は この人しか頼れないのに―
I thought, "This is the only man
I can turn to. What can I do for him?"
どうしたらいいの？ ってね
And later on, I learned the
real reason for Jiguro's tears.
そして そのあとで
ジグロが泣いた 本当の訳を知った
The second assassin that
Logsam had sent after us...
ログサムが放った２番目の男は―
...was Jiguro's closest friend
among all the King's Spears.
王の槍の中でも 特に
ジグロと親しい友人だったんだ…
（チャグム）そんな！
But, no...
（バルサ）ログサムって男は
つくづく恐ろしい―
Logsam was an
utterly fearsome man...
...and he was utterly
without scruples.
そして つくづく汚い男だった
いったん ヨゴの街に
戻った私たちは―
We returned to the Yogo city,
and from a Kanbal migrant worker...
カンバルから
出稼ぎに来ていた男から―
父が殺されたという話を聞いた
...we learned that my
father had been killed.
いつかまた 父に会えるだろうと
思っていた私は―
I had always thought that I would
see my father again someday.
For the first time since
we left Kanbal, I cried.
カンバルを出てから 初めて泣いた
それは子供の私には
あまりにも―
For someone at my age, that was
the worst possible news I could hear.
むごい話だったからね
Jiguro then told me
everything that was going on...
（バルサ）ジグロは
まるで大人に話すように―
全ての事情を話してくれたよ
...almost as if he were
speaking to an adult.
なぜ 父が殺されたのか―
He explained why my father
had been killed...
...and why I had had to
flee the country with him.
なぜ 私がジグロと
逃げなければならなかったのかをね
The hatred that blossomed
inside my heart that day...
あのとき
心に芽生えた憎しみは―
...still sits like a lump
deep inside me.
今も 心の底に
しこりとなって残っている
いつか 必ずログサムに
復讐(ふくしゅう)するという あの思いは…
That wish to get my revenge
against Logsam one day.
So I asked Jiguro to
teach me martial arts.
それで私は ジグロに
武術を教えてくれと頼んだよ
Jiguro! Teach me how to fight!
ジグロ！ 私に武術を教えて！
（バルサ）でも ジグロは
首を縦には振らなかった
But Jiguro wouldn't
agree to my request.
ダメだ
No.
The martial arts
are a man's domain.
武術は 男のものだ
どんなに頑張ってみても
女の筋肉では大したことはできない
Women's muscles prevent them...
...from making any real headway
no matter how hard they try.
And most of all, you're just a child.
それに 何よりお前は子供だ
（バルサ）そうはっきり言われても
私は諦められなかった
Even though he'd turned me down
so bluntly, I couldn't give up.
それからは 事あるごとに
ジグロの稽古を盗み見して―
From then on, I secretly watched
Jiguro train whenever I got the chance...
なんとか 短槍の使い方を
学ぼうとした
...to try to pick up how
to use a short spear.
その後 ジグロは
隊商の護衛をすることになった
Some time after that...
...Jiguro was working as an
escort for a merchant caravan.
For us, this killed three
birds with one stone.
それは私たちに 一石三鳥の
利益を もたらしてくれた
１つは ジグロの武術の
腕を生かして生計を立てられたこと
The first was that it allowed Jiguro
to make a living using his martial arts.
The second was that
I was continuously...
２つ目は ジグロの実戦を
絶えず目の当たりにできたこと
...able to witness
Jiguro in combat firsthand.
This gave me invaluable
insight into the martial arts.
これは本当に
武術の勉強になったよ
And the third was that this allowed us
to quickly gather information...
そして ３つ目は―
私たちを追っている者たちの情報を
いち早く得られたこと
...on the people
who were pursuing us.
俺たちを捜しているらしい６人…？
Six people apparently
searching for us?
Jiguro, look!
（バルサ）ジグロ 見て！
ジグロの構え！
These are your moves, Jiguro!
（バルサ）周りの大人たちが
喜ぶのを見て調子に乗っちゃってね
Seeing the amused looks on the
faces of the adults around me...
...caused me to get carried away.
あのとき ジグロの槍を
持つ手を狙ってきたでしょう？
That man went for your
spear hand, remember?
And you let go of your spear for a
second, dodged his strike, and then...
そしたら ジグロは
いったん槍を離してかわし…
二度とやるんじゃない
分かったな！
Don't ever do that again!
Is that clear?
Why did you do that?
（チャグム）
なぜ そんなことをしたの？
Who can say? I'm not really sure.
さあ どうしてかね
ジグロの心配そうな顔を見て
自分も力になりたかったのか
Maybe after seeing the worried
look on his face, I wanted to help.
ひょっとしたら 少し困らせて
やろうと思ったのかもしれないね
Or maybe I just wanted
to get a rise out of him.
After all, that man never
talked to me about anything.
なんせ 何にも
話してくれない人だったから…
（バルサ）
でも それからしばらくして―
But not long after that, Jiguro
began to train me in the martial arts.
ジグロが武術を
教えてくれるようになったんだ
え…？ どうして？
Why?
I think that one reason is that he was
impressed by my little performance.
１つは 私のパフォーマンスに
感心したからだと思う
At the time, I had no idea that
what I did was extraordinary...
当時は それがすごいことだなんて
全然分からなかったけど―
...but apparently, I had
a gift for the martial arts.
どうやら 私には
武術の才能があったらしい
なにせ 私は ジグロの戦い方を―
At any rate, I had
pretty much memorized...
...all of Jiguro's fighting
moves just by watching.
ほとんど そのまま
暗記していたんだからね
それに もう１つ 別の理由もあった
But there was something else.
One other reason.
別の… 理由…？
Another reason?
（ジグロ）
今日から これで練習しろ
Starting today, practice with this.
短槍は 体に合わせて作らない
A short spear isn't
created to fit a body.
You must make
your body fit the spear.
体を短槍に合わせるんだ
Why the change of heart?
（トロガイ）
どういう風の吹き回しだい
その娘には 血まみれの人生を―
I thought you didn't want to force
the girl to live a life of bloodshed.
歩ませたくなかったんじゃ
ないのかい？
確かに 武術を知る者は
それを極めれば極めるほど―
It's true that for any
student of the martial arts...
...the more proficient you become...
...the more opponents
you draw to yourself.
戦う相手を 吸い寄せてしまう
As much as I hate to say it,
this path is her only hope of survival.
でも この先
こいつが生きていかれる道は―
残念ながら これしかない…
ハァ… 気付いちまったのかい
そのことに…
You've figured that out, have you?
Jiguro must have already
caught wind of the rumors...
（バルサ）あのとき ジグロは―
残りの王の槍が 一団となって
私たちを捜しているってウワサを―
...that the remaining King's Spears
had joined forces to hunt us down.
すでに 耳にしていたんだろうね
And so, he began
training me in the martial arts...
それで もし
自分が死んだとしても―
私が１人で生きていけるようにと
武術を教え始めた
...so that I would be able to
survive in the event of his death.
Even so, Jiguro
was a cautious man.
それでも
ジグロは慎重な男だからね
できれば 仲間との殺し合いは
避けたいと考えていたから―
He hoped to avoid having to kill
any more of his friends if he could...
あまり大っぴらに
用心棒の仕事はせず―
...so we lived up in Yogo's
mountains until our money ran out...
金がなくなるまではヨゴの山の中で
暮らすようにしていたのさ
...and didn't take on any
high-profile bodyguard jobs.
Ah, and that's when you met
Tanda and Mistress Torogai.
（チャグム）そのころに タンダや
トロガイ師と出会ったんだね
Right.
（バルサ）
ああ おかげで私たちは―
Living that way allowed us
to evade the pursuit...
それから 10年近くは
王の槍の追跡をやり過ごし―
...of the King's Spears
for nearly ten years.
Our life was pleasant enough,
although dangerous.
危険だが 結構楽しい暮らしを
続けることができたんだ
But then the six
King's Spears came, right?
でも…
６人の王の槍が来たのか…？
Yes.
なにせ 若い女を連れた―
When a skilled spear-wielder...
...with a young woman in tow
takes on bodyguard jobs...
腕利きの短槍使いが
用心棒を続けてりゃ―
...word is going to get around
whether you want it to or not.
嫌でも ウワサは
広まっちまうからね
On the way home after a big job...
大きな仕事を終えた帰り道―
とうとう 私たちの行動範囲を
調べ続けていた王の槍たちに―
...we were finally
discovered by the King's Spears...
...who had been tracking
our activities all that time.
見つかっちまったのさ
（ジグロ）
お前は 向こうの岩場に隠れていろ
Go hide in those rocks over there.
Go!
行け！
I was reluctant to leave him.
（バルサ）私は 不本意だった
I had believed that I would be
able to help Jiguro, at least a little...
少しは ジグロを
助けられると思っていたのに―
いざ 王の槍と対峙(たいじ)したとき
何もできなかったんだからね
...but when the time came
to face the King's Spears...
...I wasn't able to do anything.
No, even if I had
been able to help...
いや 仮に何かできたとしても―
ジグロが
そうさせなかったのかもしれない
...I'm certain that Jiguro
wouldn't have let me.
（ジグロ）
よせ！ こんなことは無益だ！
Stop! This will accomplish nothing!
（バルサ）ジグロは あのとき
すでに覚悟を決めていたんだ
Jiguro had already
made up his mind.
王の槍とは 自分１人で戦おうって
He would fight the
King's Spears alone.
Listen to me! Put away
your spears and return to Kanbal!
（ジグロ）悪いことは言わん！
今すぐ槍を収めてカンバルへ帰れ！
How long do you intend to
continue such a futile endeavor?
こんな不毛なことを
いつまで続ける気だ！
Jiguro had decided that
he wouldn't allow my hands...
（バルサ）ジグロは 私の手を
無益な殺し合いで汚させまいと―
そう決めていたんだよ…
...to be stained
by senseless killing.
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
From Jiguro to Balsa.
From Balsa to Chagum.
Inherited desires. Tested bonds.
Next time, "Season of Awakening."
Episode 22
Season of Awakening
Spring is almost upon us.